[Music]
Professor D Dave and CH here we should
remember quite a bit about acids and
bases especially the Bron stead Lowry
model which is the model of acidity and
basicity we will most frequently use
describing acidbase reactions in the
context of proton transfer but there is
another model that we will sometimes be
using in organic chemistry and that is
the Lewis model let's review this model
as well since it will be relevant to a
number of important mechanisms we see
later rather than focusing on proton
transfer this model looks at electrons
alouis acid is a substance which accepts
a pair of electrons while a Lewis base
is one which donates a pair of electrons
in truth there isn't much difference
between a Lewis base and a bron stad
Lowry base as even when proton transfer
is involved it requires a lone pair from
some base which can coordinate to the
proton hence an electron pair donor but
the difference is quite significant when
looking at aets because the leis model
will often involve a base coordinating
to some atom rather than accepting a
proton for example let's look at Boron
Tri fluide BF3 this Boron atom has a
substantial partial positive charge
because of the polarity of these Boron
Florine bonds because of this electron
deficiency it is prone to attack by
electrons since positive charges and
negative charges attract which is
essentially the central theme of the
entire field of chemistry so a lwi base
like this fluoride ion can attack the
Boron atom to form a new Bond leaving us
with BF4 minus we will call this product
an acid base adduct so we won't get
conjugate species like with the Bron
stead Lowry model one of the reasons
this is relevant in organic chemistry is
that we will frequently see metal cat I
acting as Lewis acids take the Magnesium
2+ ion
this is electron deficient due to the
formal positive charge so electrons can
coordinate to it this means that we can
often find metal cations like this
coordinated to Regions with a formal
negative charge on certain kinds of
molecules especially
oxyanion like here with this phosphate
ion transition metals also frequently
form Lewis acids compounds like
ti4
fecl3
zncl2 and sncl4 are all Lewis acids due
to having a central electron deficient
atom which is susceptible to attack from
a LS base again with bases things are
not much different conceptually from a
bron dead Lowry base the difference is
that a Lewis base doesn't specifically
have to coordinate to a proton it can
coordinate to something else and will
still qualify as a LS base many oxygen
and nitrogen containing compounds can
act as Lewis bases due to the lone pair
of electrons on these atoms as well as
sulfur with that we should have a basic
understanding of the Lewis model for
acidity and basicity as well as some
important examples of Lewis acids that
will come up as we study organic
chemistry professor Dave for che see you
next time